<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A perfume against the noysome pestilence prescribed by Moses vnto Aaron. Num. 16. 46. Written by Roger Fenton, preacher of Grayes Inne.</title>
            <author>Fenton, Roger, 1565-1616.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1603</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00667</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10800</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105577</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841304</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841304</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5879</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00667)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5879)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 773:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A perfume against the noysome pestilence prescribed by Moses vnto Aaron. Num. 16. 46. Written by Roger Fenton, preacher of Grayes Inne.</title>
                  <author>Fenton, Roger, 1565-1616.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[96] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By R. R[ead] for William Aspley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1603.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"A prayer for this time of visitation", C2r-D11r.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D¹² .</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Numbers XVI, 46 --  Commentaries.</term>
               <term>Plague --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5879:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5879:1"/>
            <p>A <hi>Perfume</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Peſtilence,</hi> preſcribed by <hi>Moſes</hi> vnto <hi>Aaron.</hi> Num. 16. 46.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>Roger Fenton,</hi> Preacher of Grayes Inne.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at <hi>London by</hi> R. R. <hi>for</hi> William Aſpley. 1603.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:5879:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5879:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the Chriſtian</hi> Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe times of Gods viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on doe begge that at my hands which otherwiſe, in this writing age, might very well haue bin ſpared: the publiſhing of ſome few Meditations concerning the times, for the inſtruction and comfort of ſuch as ſhall now ſtand in need of the ſame. And albeit it ſeemeth to me a matter of great difficultie to preſcribe formes of priuate prayer for others, ſince I haue not the ſcantling of any ones
<pb facs="tcp:5879:3"/> affection but mine owne: yet becauſe this Treatiſe promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth ſomewhat in that kinde: I haue annexed three ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations: which if they may fit thy deuotion (gentle rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) I ſhall be right glad: If not, I wiſh thee that which may togither with all ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all comfort in life and death, to the glorie of God in Chriſt Ieſus our Lord,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. F.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Auguſt.</hi> 9. 1603.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:5879:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Perfume against</hi> the noiſome Peſtilence <hi>preſcribed by</hi> Moſes vnto <hi>Aaron.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Num. 16. 46.</bibl>
               <q>Take the Cenſer and put fire therein of the Altar, put Incenſe thereon, and go quickly to the congregation, and make an atonement for them: for there is vvrath gone out from the Lord. The plague is begun.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His plague as it is a generall iudgment zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vpon all ſorts, and ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring none: ſo it is inflicted for a generall ſin, as appeareth by the remedie; in that the atonement is made for the whole congregation. And who muſt make the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonement but <hi>Aaron</hi> himſelfe, the party offended? aduiſed by
<pb facs="tcp:5879:4"/> 
               <hi>Moſes;</hi> againſt whom alſo all the multitude of the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> murmured, and made inſurrection, <hi>verſe</hi> 41. 42.</p>
            <p>This atonement is preſcribed by <hi>Moſes,</hi> and put in execution by <hi>Aaron,</hi> after this maner.</p>
            <p n="1">1 He taketh the Cenſer, a hallowed veſſell for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, kept in the holieſt place of the Tabernacle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. 4.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He put fire therein to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue the odours, not common fire, but taken from the Altar, where it burned continually, to ſignifie how ready God is to anſwer vs by fire, and to accept our deuotions, if we be not ſlack in bringing of them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He putteth Incenſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Incenſe compounded of ſweet Spices; to wit, Myrrhe, cleare Gumme, Galbandum, <note place="margin">Exod. 30. 34.</note> and pure Frankincenſe, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed
<pb facs="tcp:5879:4"/> after the Arte of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecarie: bruſed and beaten to powder, to make a more fragrant ſmell. This is the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonement which muſt bee made with expedition; becauſe <hi>wrath is gone out from the Lord,</hi> therefore there is no delaying: and to proue that <hi>wrath is gone out,</hi> he vſeth a ſenſible demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration in that <hi>the plague is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of which context, that we may ſo diſpoſe, as may be moſt eaſie for our vnderſtanding; we propound in the firſt place, the iudgement it ſelfe which now beginneth to bee made ſenſible vnto vs: Secondly we enquire of the cauſe thereof; and how it begunne? in that <hi>wrath is gone out from the Lord.</hi> In the third place we adde the remedie; the atonement made
<pb facs="tcp:5879:5"/> according to the preſcript of <hi>Moſes, Take the Cenſer, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>1.</head>
               <p>The word which commonly is vſed in Scripture for the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence, <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Leuit. 16. 25. Num. 14. 12. Deut. 28. 21. 2. Sam. 24 13.</note> is deriued from a verbe that ſignifieth to ſpeake, as ſome thinke, becauſe, where it is, euery one ſpeaketh of it, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth after it, how it encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, what remedies there be for it, what preſeruatiues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, what be the ſymp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomes, &amp; qualities of it: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſince it is a thing ſo well knowne, as euery one is able to diſcourſe of it; I ſhall need to ſpeake the leſſe. Onely thus much in a word: ſince we haue ſo long hardened our harts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the voice of God, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnto vs; it ſeemeth now
<pb facs="tcp:5879:5"/> that hee will indeede ſpeake with vs, in a iudgement ſo quick, that vnleſſe ſome ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die atonement be made with all expedition; hee is but a <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> worde and a blow: that ſince we would not heare him, we ſhall now feele him, for the word which <hi>Moſes</hi> here vſeth (properly tranſlated Plague) ſignifieth Smiting: and ſuch a ſmiting as is fearefull and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible for impenitent ſinners to thinke vpon. Fearfull, becauſe it brings death with it: and without repentance a ſecond death. Fearefull, in regarde of the terrours which accompany the ſame: for which cauſe <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> calleth it <hi>The Peſtilence</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 91. 5</note> 
                  <hi>that walketh in the darkeneſſe;</hi> taking vs vnawares when we cannot ſee to auoide it: cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſuch wofull lamentations
<pb facs="tcp:5879:6"/> of diſtreſſed ſoules, that periſh for want of ſuccour; ſuch dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full griping, and towling of Bels, as would make a ſluggard watchfull, or a ſound man ſicke to heare. Fearfull for the noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomneſſe of it, which depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth men of the comforte of that friendly and neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like viſitation, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they might enioy. Feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, becauſe it ſtrikes ſuddenly (which made <hi>Aaron</hi> make ſuch haſt) diſappointing vs thereby of many bleſſings, which a deliberate death would endowe vs withall; for the perfitting of our repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; for the better triall and exerciſe of our faith and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; for the bleſſing of our poſteritie, and the more effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall enforming of others, by the laſt words which make the
<pb facs="tcp:5879:6"/> deepeſt impreſſion; for the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of our minds, in ſetting our houſes in order, &amp; making choiſe of the fitteſt ſoile where the laſt ſeed of charitie might be ſowne. Fearefull, in regarde of the vniuerſality of it; ſpare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">Luk. 16. 9</note> neither place nor perſon: for as it is a ſword pointing to <note place="margin">1. Sam. 24 ver. 19. Pſal. 91. verſ. 5.</note> the citie &amp; cutting neere hand; ſo is it an arrow flying into the country and ſmiting a farre of. And if any be ſo ſenceleſſe as not to be mooued with this fearefull iudgement, let them remember that Chriſt recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth this but amongſt <hi>the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings of ſorrow, Math.</hi> 24. 8. <note place="margin">Mat. 24. 8</note> ſignifying that God hath yet moe arrowes in his quiuer, and greater vengeance in ſtore to make an end of ſuch wretches as make no vſe of theſe begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:5879:7"/>
               <head>2.</head>
               <p>That the Plague is begun, is a thing well knowne, but how it begun is the queſtion.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Some take it to be a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commoditie brought ouer in our Marchants commodities from forreine countries.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Others ſuppoſe it to be a conſequent of drought, and of that want of moiſture which wee haue complained of ſo long.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Some imagine it to be a matter of courſe, whereas the elements gather infection con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually more or leſſe, once in certaine yeares gathering to a head, it muſt needes breake forth.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Some take it to be an vnhappie coniunction of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb facs="tcp:5879:7"/> Planets, inflaming the ayre vnnaturally.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Others conceaue, that a huge concourſe of people in ſome extremitie of heat and drought, hath inflamed and corrupted the bloud, and ſo it begun.</p>
               <p>But the iudgement of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> reacheth further, in that he maketh it an effect of Gods wrath: for whatſoeuer ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darie cauſes doe concurre here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, certaine it is, that the wrath of God is the principall: which being kindled and ſent forth, doth fire the reſt and ſet them all a working. He is purblind, as the Apoſtle ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 2. Pet. 1. 9</note> and cannot ſee a farre off, who looketh onely vpon infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour cauſes for if the cauſe of this infection were elementa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, why muſt holy fire be taken
<pb facs="tcp:5879:8"/> from the Altar? fire out of the chimney would purifie that &amp; perfume the ayre as well as any: it muſt be celeſtiall fire; which argueth that the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall cauſe is ſupernall.</p>
               <p>The wrath of God once kindled is terrible: when <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> did but thinke of it, it put him into a paſſion like men who aſtoniſhed &amp; halfe frigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vſe to bleſſe themſelues, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. 12. <hi>If his wrath be kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 2. 12</note> 
                  <hi>yea but a little, bleſsed are all they that truſt in him.</hi> Tis like Gun powder which bloweth vp whole familes before they liue out halfe their dayes.</p>
               <p>But much more terrible is it, when wrath thus kindled is gone out from the Lord; as in this place where the plague is begun: for long it is before it goe forth: therefore when it is
<pb facs="tcp:5879:8"/> once out, a harder matter to driue it backe againe. It hath a time to kindle, and a long time: for <hi>God is ſlowe to anger.</hi> After it is kindled in the breaſt it hath a time to breake forth, in words and threats: for <hi>Hee ſpeaketh vnto vs in his anger</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>he vex vs in his ſore diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 2. 5</note> After many threatnings and warnings: he hath a time to prepare himſelfe to battell, to <hi>whet his ſword, and bend his bow, and make his arrowes ready,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 32. 23. 34.</note> which are ruſtie and blunt, and all out of order. A time to <hi>open his ſtorehouſe, and vnſeale his treaſuries,</hi> where all his plagues &amp; inſtruments of death be hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vp, &amp; hardly drawne from him: he is more liberall of his bleſſing, they come from him with leſſe adoe: for he neither ſealeth them in his treaſure,
<pb facs="tcp:5879:9"/> nor locketh them in his cheſt, nor keepeth them in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, but carieth them in his hands: <hi>It is the opening of his hands and all things liuing are</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 145. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>filled with plenteouſneſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Doubtleſſe then, it is no ſmall matter that hath kindled the wrath of God againſt vs: no cordes of vanitie, but ſome Cart-ropes of iniquitie, which pull downe this iudgement from him. Which thing ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth, as well by the nature of the remedie here preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, as by the qualitie of the iudgement inflicted.</p>
               <p>Here is Incenſe to perfume and ſweeten: therefore ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what there is which ſtincketh in the noſthrils of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, in that <hi>Aaron</hi> muſt diſſolue ſuch ſweete Odoures for the atonement. Secondly the noi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:5879:9"/> of the Peſtilence, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the cauſe thereof to bee ſome loathſome abhominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which cauſeth God to turne the light of his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance from vs, as we turne our faces from perſons and places infected:</p>
               <p n="1">1. Whether it be therfore our prophaneneſſe and neglect of Gods ſeruice: which <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> thought ſufficient to cauſe God to meete vs with the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence, <hi>Exod.</hi> 5. 3.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Or whether it be our hipocriticall worſhip of God diſſembling with him in our hearts as the <hi>Iſralites</hi> did, for which they ſhould dye of the Peſtilence, <hi>Iero.</hi> 42. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0. <hi>vlt.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Or whether it be our light accoumpt of the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the vnworthy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing thereof which cauſed
<pb facs="tcp:5879:10"/> ſuch a mortalitie amongſt the <hi>Corinthians.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 30.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Or whether our ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much confidence in ſecondary cauſes (in that God of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie hath laid the corner ſtone, and vnited kingdomes toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) make vs to number the people as <hi>Dauid</hi> did, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure our ſelues in the ſtrength thereof; which cauſeth God by this kinde of iudgement to ſubſtract (as faſt as we multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie) from <hi>Dan</hi> to <hi>Berſheba.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Or whether our ſtubber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in not making vſe of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer viſitations hath brought greater vpon vs as vpon the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in <hi>Amos.</hi> 4. for God hath proceeded in the ſame order with vs as with them. Firſt ſending vs famine, as <hi>ver.</hi> 6. after that drought wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we haue long complained,
<pb facs="tcp:5879:10"/> as <hi>verſ.</hi> 7. thirdly want of fruite this laſt yeare, as <hi>verſ.</hi> 9. and now the Peſtilence, <hi>verſe</hi> 10. and if for all this we will not turne vnto him, there remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth worſe behinde; warre, and the ouerthrowe of <hi>Sodom. verſe</hi> 11.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Or whether the tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch vncleane and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious harlots as keepe about this place, haue infected the Citie: for the Plague ceaſeth not in Iſrael till <hi>Phineas</hi> had done iudgement vpon thoſe adulterous perſons, <hi>Num.</hi> 25. 8.</p>
               <p>Vnto which you may adde thoſe wanton attyres and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemelie faſhions wherein our women diſguiſe themſelues: whoſe ornaments do beautifie their <hi>Aegyptian</hi> Temples (not Temples of the holy Ghoſt) but where ſome Crocodile
<pb facs="tcp:5879:11"/> or poyſenfull ſerpent doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habite, whoſe gallant buſhes of ſuch curious and coſtlie haire doe hang out to teſtifie that their Wine is of the Vine of <hi>Sodome,</hi> and Grapes of <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morah,</hi> commonly ſolde at the ſigne of the Painted face and naked breſt. Theſe creatures when they thinke themſelues moſt ſweete and fine, then be they moſt loathſome and vgly in the ſight of God and honeſt men.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Or whether ſome trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous conſpiracie plotted and intended by ſome mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring male-contents for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> to the great perill or ouerthrow of Church or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, as it was in this place, <hi>verſe</hi> 41.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Or whether the blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
<pb facs="tcp:5879:11"/> of affected <hi>Atheiſts</hi> hath poyſoned our ayre: for while they be ſuffered to breath in a Chriſtian common-wealth, they muſt needs infect vs, ſince in the iudgement of a Heathen Prince, to blaſpheme the true God was accompted moſt fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie abhomination; inſomuch as he decreed their houſes to bee made a Iakes, who ſpake anye plaſphemie againſt the God of <hi>Shadracke, Meſhake,</hi> and <hi>Abedmago. Dan.</hi> 3. 29.</p>
               <p>Whether theſe, or all theſe togither, certes ſome loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and abhominable ſinnes they be, which haue brought ſo noyſome a iudgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, which muſt be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumed by the incenſe of ſweet odours.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:5879:12"/>
               <head>3.</head>
               <p>And what is <hi>Aaron</hi> that he ſhould make an atonement for ſo great matters? a ſinfull man like one of vs. He was but a ſhadow, the true Prieſt is the ſonne of God our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, by whoſe onely vertue the atonement made euen by <hi>Aaron</hi> himſelfe was made ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable vnto God.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt this Prieſt of the High God, in the fulneſſe of time tooke the Cenſer, when he aſſumed our humane nature into the perſonall vnion of his deitie, when he hallowed and ſanctified that earthen veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell to offer Incenſe therein vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Father.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He put fire in this Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, not ſparingly, but in ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:5879:12"/> quantitie as he had like to haue burnt vp Cenſer and all, <hi>Iohn</hi> 2. 17. <hi>The zeale of thine houſe</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 2. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>hath conſumed me.</hi> That fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent affection alſo which he carryed to mankinde, was fire enough to diſſolue Odours for a thouſand worldes. It hath beene obſerued, that as the Sonne of God when hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came man made choiſe of the worthier ſex, that ſuch a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice might be without the leaſt note of imperfection: ſo one the other ſide did he vouchſafe to be conceaued of a woman without a Father, that hee might ſuck from her ſuch ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe of affection as that ſex could deriue vpon him. And yet he receiued more then ſhe could giue; forſomuch as her nature was ſinfull, and ſinne doth naturally harden the hart
<pb facs="tcp:5879:13"/> and dull the affection<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Chriſt therefore who receiued all but ſinne, muſt needes haue his loue and affection much more quickned towardes man: for whoſe ſake it pleaſed him to bee humbled with ſuch paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Humaine affection is fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent for the time, but vncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, like earthly fire, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in, and ſometimes out. <hi>Peter</hi> his loue was hotte e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough when hee would dye with Chriſt; but it would not holde: but Chriſt hath kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his affection from the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, from a perpetual fire which neuer went out. Humane loue ſauoureth of the earth bee it neuer ſo pure, except the holy Ghoſt doe ſanctifie it from aboue. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpake from loue and from an harty kinde affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:5879:13"/> to his maiſter, I make no doubt; willing him to fauour himſelfe that ſuch miſeries might not befall him; but his loue was not taken from the Altar, it ſeemeth by Chriſt his anſwer to haue beene kindled from hell rather <hi>get thee behind me Sathan.</hi> But Chriſt in whom the holy Ghoſt dwelleth bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, is full of celeſtiall fire.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Wherevpon he putteth Incenſe, offering vp prayer vnto his Father an atonement for his whole Church; Incenſe compounded of ſweete O<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dours, artificially compounded of ſuch deuine meditations as are recorded in the 17. chapter of Saint <hi>John,</hi> in that excellent prayer made by Chriſt, for the entire myſticall body, himſelfe and his members. Theſe ſpices were bruſed, broken, &amp; beaten
<pb facs="tcp:5879:14"/> to powder, to the end they might ſend vp a more odori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferous ſmell, into the noſthrils of his heauenly Father. Were not the thoughts of his heart broken, when lamenting ouer <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> in this maner. <hi>If</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 19. 42.</note> 
                  <hi>thou haddeſt knowne at the least in this thy day thoſe things which belong vnto thy peace,</hi> there commeth a ſob and cutteth away the reſt of the ſentence, and as if his minde were bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the midſt betwixt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion and indignation, hee concludeth: <hi>but now are they hid from thine eyes.</hi> Were not his deuine Meditations inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, and ſore bruſed, when hee ſtood in a mammering what to ſay, backward and forward: when hee ſaith, and againe vnſaith, <hi>How is my</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. 12. 27.</note> 
                  <hi>ſoule troubled, what ſhall I ſay?</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5879:14"/> 
                  <hi>Father ſaue me from this houre; but therefore came I into this houre: Father glorifie thy name.</hi> Nay were not the paſſions of his heart beaten to powder, in that bitter agonie and bloudie conflict, where he ſtriueth till he ſweate, and ſweateth till he bleed: ſo bruſed and broken in hart, that an Angell muſt comfort the Lord of life.</p>
               <p n="5">5. This ſweete Incenſe is an atonement to his Father: but for whome? for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of men, who mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mured<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> conſpired, and made in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection againſt him; for his enemies and bloudie perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors. Yea the firſt Incenſe of prayer which he offered vpon the croſſe, was for thoſe who nailed him to the croſſe, <hi>Father forgiue them, for they wotte not</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 23. 34.</note> 
                  <hi>what they doe:</hi> and not for
<pb facs="tcp:5879:15"/> them onely, but for all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde was this atonement made, who pierced the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall God before he had a ſide to pierce, <hi>Zacher.</hi> 12. 10. and <note place="margin">Zak<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 12. 10.</note> becauſe wee cannot conceiue how our ſinne ſhould pierce a ſpirit, or our ill dooing extend vnto God more then our well dooing, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16. 2. Therefore <note place="margin">Pſal. 16. 2</note> God is incarnate, and hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken our fleſh vpon him, that man might conceaue, and ſee, and looke vpon him whom he hath pierced.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonement made once for all; yet we ſee wrath is gone out from the Lord, and the plague is begun amongſt vs: <hi>Aaron</hi> with his Cenſer, and all the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies of the Leuiticall Prieſthood be vaniſhed, what remedy remaineth then for vs?
<pb facs="tcp:5879:15"/> Much euery waye: for albeit the Aaronicall Prieſthood be taken away, and the true Prieſt aſcended vp on high out of ſight: yet notwithſtanding by vertue of his mediation there is a continuall entercourſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Throne of God &amp; his Church militant here vpon earth: for his heauenly inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, and our holye deſires are as ſo many aſcending, and deſcending Angels of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce betweene God and vs And as teaching bringeth vs to know the <hi>truth</hi> of God, ſo prayer teſtifieth that wee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge his <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> to be the onely fountaine of all bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings: wherefore as there is nothing to which God is more prone, and inclinable then to communicate his goodneſſe; inſomuch as the Prophet ſaith,
<pb facs="tcp:5879:16"/> he doth <hi>expect and waite that he may haue mercy:</hi> ſo there is <note place="margin">Eſa. 30. 18</note> no part of our ſeruice can be more acceptable vnto God then this of prayer, which drawing mercie from him, ſheweth ſo happy a concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene his will and our wiſhes. It is with our gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and mercifull Father in this caſe, as with a full breaſt, which aketh for deſire to giue Milke: then welcome is the hungrie childe that can ſucke the beſt.</p>
               <p>This dutie lieth principallie vpon the Miniſters of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, who as publique perſons doe ſtand and ſpeake in the preſence of God for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: for as it was enioyned <hi>Aaron</hi> and his ſonnes to bleſſe the people in the name of God; and to offer prayers vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:5879:16"/> God in the name of the people: ſo was the ſame prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed in the Primatiue Church (as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſeth) by the Miniſter of this function: <note place="margin">1. Cor. 14 16.</note> whoſe Prayers and thankes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuings the people by their ioyfull acclamation did rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie: Wherefore the Arche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſters of the Goſpell, the <note place="margin">Acts. 6. 3.</note> twelue Apoſtles, ſeperating others for other imployments, reſerued themſelues wholye for <hi>Prayer and the Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Verſe 4.</note> 
                  <hi>of the worde,</hi> conioyning thoſe two ghoſtlye exerciſes together; as if they whoſe care and charge ouer the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, is manifolde more, then common perſons, ſhould haue a double portion in this du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Prayer for the people: which verye dutye impoſed vppon them, is a ſpeciall
<pb facs="tcp:5879:17"/> ſeale and confirmation, that the ſelfe ſame deuine loue which hath made choiſe of the inſtrument, will thereby effect his good worke, in bleſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſing his people, and accepting their prayers and vnfained de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotions: but ſo much the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if the Miniſter himſelfe doe <hi>lift vp pure hands in prayer.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. Tim. 2. 8.</note> Wherefore our great deſire is, that as wee for the people, ſo they for vs would pray with <hi>Dauid, Let thy Prieſts (O Lorde) be cloathed with righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 132. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>ſo ſhall thy Saints re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce and ſing.</hi> Which oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that it may be the more ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall, and acceptable vnto God; for externall incenſe, we muſt take vnto vs the Cenſer of the Sacrament, thoſe hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed myſteries which repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and exhibite vnto vs the
<pb facs="tcp:5879:17"/> precious body of our bleſſed Sauiour, which neuer com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth emptie of heauenly fire taken from the Altar: for <hi>it is</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ioh 6. 63</note> 
                  <hi>the ſpirit that quickneth, the fleſh profiteth nothing:</hi> Whereby our odours of deuotion being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly kindled and diſſolued, our Incenſe ſhall aſcend euen as pillers of ſmoake in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and couer the mercie ſeate.</p>
               <p>Yet for all this let the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple take heed how by confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the burthen of this dutie vpon the Miniſter, they doe any way ſeeke to exonerate or eaſe themſelues: for concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſpirituall function of offering this Incenſe of prayer we are all of vs Prieſts at large. <hi>A choſen generation and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Pet. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Reu. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 10</note> 
                  <hi>royall Prieſt hood,</hi> ordained and made Prieſts vnto God by the
<pb facs="tcp:5879:18"/> Lambe which now ſitteth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Throne.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Let euery one therefore bring his Cenſer, that is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> his hart vnto the Lord, a hallowed &amp; ſanctified veſſell for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, to offer vp incenſe of prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er vnto God, a veſſell laid vp in the holy of holies, in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly tabernacle, where Chriſt <note place="margin">Heb<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o. 3. 2</note> ſitteth at the right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Let him put fire in the ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, the fire of zeale that he may be feruent in Prayer; for the wrath of God waxeth hot, and our high Prieſt hath taught vs by his own exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple in his agony whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hand of God is vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, <note place="margin">Luk. 22. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> then to pray more earneſtly.</p>
               <p n="3">3. But alas we knowe not what nor how to pray: happily we ſhall pray for life, becauſe that is ſweet vnto vs, or for our houſhold and friends, for that
<pb facs="tcp:5879:18"/> they are deere vnto vs, or ſome ſuch like petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which fleſh &amp; blood in this caſe ſhall reueale vnto vs: neither do we know in theſe extremities how to limit our praiers according to the wil of our heauenly father: neither will our earthly fire of carnall zeale carye the ſmoake of our incenſe high inough <hi>to couer the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 16. 13</note> 
                  <hi>mercy ſeat,</hi> beſides euery blaſt of winde, euery idle &amp; wandring cogitation wil be ready to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perce it into the ayre before e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it come neere the clouds wherefore we muſt beg ſome holy fire fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Altar: &amp; deſire God with <hi>Dauid,</hi> that he wold <hi>direct our prayers in his ſight like Incenſe,</hi> that they might aſcend directly without interruption<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whereof aſſurance is made by the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 20. <hi>The ſpirit alſo helpeth our infirmities,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5879:19"/> 
                  <hi>for we know not what to may as we ought, but the ſpirit it ſelfe maketh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d to God for v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> to be expreſſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4 Vpon this holy fire muſt we put incence: that is, <hi>powre out our ſoules before God,</hi> and our prayers in his preſence: not caſting forth vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uerently before his throne our ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fection, or what euer our hart luſteth: nor preſenting before ſuch a maieſtie, whatſoeuer our fooliſh conceite doth ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt for the preſent: but our incenſe muſt be compounded or ſweete odours, and artifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally made after the skill of the Apothecary. Choiſe and ſelect Meditations are to be proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by mature premeditation, compoſed according to the praeſcript of our Lorde and maſter; who hath not onely
<pb facs="tcp:5879:19"/> giuen v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> generall directions, and rules of ſupplication<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but alſo framed for vs a generall ſumme, an exact forme, and moſt perfit patterne of all prayer.</p>
               <p>Theſe Odours muſt bee bruſed or beaten to powder<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>A ſacrifice of God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> a troubled ſpirit, a contrite and broken hart</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>O God wilt not thou deſpiſe.</hi> It is no ſmall griefe which breakes the hart, no ſleight humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which brings vs to duſt and powder. We ſay we are ſorrie for our ſinnes; but we cannot weepe: ſorrie, but we eate and drinke neuer the leſſe: we ſigh and ſay our prayers, and by and by as cheerefull and light harted as euer before. Theſe ſudden qualmes be farre from that humiliation and contriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which the Scripture calleth
<pb facs="tcp:5879:20"/> the <hi>breaking</hi> and the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>enting of</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ioel. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 13</note> 
                  <hi>the heart:</hi> for can we perſwade our ſelues<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it is no greater tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <note place="margin">Gal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 24 Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 29.</note> then ſo, to haue our fleſh mortified yea and crucified: or can we aſſure our conſciences that we doe indeed circumciſe the foreskin of our harts, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe we feele them bleed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in vs? God propheſied by <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherie</hi> of true penitents, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they had <hi>looked vpon him whom they had pierced,</hi> and duly conſidered how their ſinnes had offended the Almightie, they <hi>ſhould lament for him, as one mourneth for his onely ſonne:</hi> and <note place="margin">Zach<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 12. 10.</note> great reaſon; that as our ſinnes had pierced him, ſo ſorrow for ſinne ſhould pierce vs: &amp; as we cauſed him to giue his ſon, his onely ſonne vnto death for vs, ſo our mourning ſhould not be ſlight &amp; ſuperficiall, but as one
<pb facs="tcp:5879:20"/> mourneth for his onely ſonne.</p>
               <p>To the end our incenſe may be beaten ſmaller, our Sauiour Chriſt hath commanded vs to ioine praier with faſting, which maketh our Incenſe both to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d higher, &amp; to ſmel ſweeter: for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> doth not only eleuate the minde in deuine meditation, which was the effect of <hi>Moſes</hi> his faſt in the mount: but in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priuing our fleſh of her ordinary food, we do worke reue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſelues for offending ſuch a gratious God, and withall giue vnfained teſtimonie, that our ſelues we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demne as the only cauſes of our own miſery. Thus diſpleaſing our ſelues we &amp; our incenſe are more pleaſing vnto God: iudging &amp; condemning our ſelues, we ſhall not be iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged; <note place="margin">2. Cor 7. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> &amp; reue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging our ſelues vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſelues, we ſhall preuent the greater iudgment of God.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:5879:21"/>
               <p> If publike faſts vpon the occaſion of this generall viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhould appeare mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly by the rules of Phiſicke, not to ſtand with ſafetie of ſome weaklings, in a time of infection: then let them per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it priuatly, that our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which ſeeth them in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, may releeue them open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie. For albeit our gratious God in regarde of our feares, and infirmities, doth diſpenſe with the maner of his worſhip in ſome caſes, as he diſpenſed with <hi>Dauid,</hi> who ſhould haue gone to <hi>Gibeon</hi> to aske counſel of God, but onely that he was <hi>afraide of the ſworde of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Chro. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 30. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Theſ. 5. 27.</note> 
                  <hi>of the Lorde:</hi> yet for the ſubſtance of his worſhip we are neuer diſpenſed withall. If we ſhould ſeriouſly thinke of theſe things, and practiſe vpon
<pb facs="tcp:5879:21"/> our ſelues to purpoſe, wee ſhould not onely preuent the Prophet his complaint, that <hi>wee hang downe our heads like a</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Bull-ruſh,</hi> which boweth in a ſtorme, and after ſtandeth pricke vp, as before: but wee ſhould finde ſuch alteration in our ſelues as wee ſhould haue ſmall liſt to commit the ſame ſinnes againe. Yea the very remembrance of them would make vs to loue our ſelues the worſe while we liued.</p>
               <p n="5">5. And as for prayer, all times are conuenient, ſo is it a generall dutie to be performed for all perſons: for the whole congregation of what condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſoeuer, <hi>Let prayers be made for all men, for Kings, and for all</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. Tim. 2. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>that be in authoritie:</hi> for our enimies, and them that riſe vp againſt vs, as in this place
<pb facs="tcp:5879:22"/> againſt <hi>Aaron:</hi> for as prayer is a benefit which none ſo poore but is able to beſtow; ſo there is none ſo rich but ſtandeth in need of it; and againe, as it is in the powre of euery one to giue; ſo is it not in the power for any one to refuſe it, thogh through malitiouſneſſe they will not vouchſafe to accept any thing at our hands, yea though they be ſet on miſchiefe againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> &amp; <hi>Aaron:</hi> yet <hi>Aaron</hi> his Incenſe ſhall ſtay the plague that is begun amongſt them.</p>
               <p>But while we ſeriouſly reflect vpon our ſelues, all that hath bin ſaid will not comfort vs: for we haue neither cenſer, nor fire nor odours for the purpoſe. Our harts which ſhould be hallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed &amp; ſanctified veſſels for this holy action, laid vp in the holy place of the tabernacle; they
<pb facs="tcp:5879:22"/> are daily and hourely propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned &amp; polluted by common &amp; vncleane vſe. Our fire the moſt of it is kindled either from the earth or a worſe place, for Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than is euer caſting his fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brands at vs, or els blowing with the bellowes of one tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation or other: and if we can beg any heauenly fire from the Altar, we haue ſo many hume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous affections, as bee ready euermore to quench the ſame. Our odours ſtinke, <hi>the imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 5. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>of our harts be only euill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually,</hi> &amp; if good motions be inſpired fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue, there is ſuch a damp <hi>of thoughts ariſing in our</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 24. 38.</note> 
                  <hi>harts</hi> to meet with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as muſt needs choake them. Yea that excellent compound of prayer made by our Sauiour Chriſt himſelfe for our vſe, if it once paſſe through our polluted lips we marre it in ſaving of it.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:5879:23"/>
               <p> And to ſay the trueth, our conſciences doe accuſe vs, and our ſinnes doe witneſſe, that we are the offendors who haue kindled this wrath of God againſt vs; and ſhall wee now take our Cenſers and offer In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe? ſo did <hi>Moſes</hi> bid the rebellious people in the 17. verſe of this Chapter; <hi>Take euery one their Cenſer and put In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Num. 16. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>thereon before the Lorde: two hundreth and fiftie Cenſers:</hi> but this is the next waye to kindle the wrath of God more againſt vs, to conſume vs as it did them, 35. verſe.</p>
               <p>It is true, if we be obſtinate in our rebellions: but other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies though <hi>Aaron</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe haue ſinned; yet we read that he may take the Cenſer as well for himſelfe as for others, and it ſhall be ſo accepted that
<pb facs="tcp:5879:23"/> 
                  <hi>the ſmoake of the Incenſe ſhall</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Leuit. 16. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>couer the mercie Seat, that is vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the teſtimonie: So he ſhall not dye.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And againſt all our infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and imperfections which can be alledged, we are relee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued aboundantly, in the 8. of the <hi>Reuelation</hi> the 3. verſe. <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Reuel. 8. 3</note> 
                  <hi>Angell ſtood before the Altar hauing a golden Cenſer, and much Odours was giuen vnto him, that he ſhould offer with the prayers of all Saints.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our high Prieſt made not an end of praying for vs vpon the Croſſe: but as he is a Prieſt for euer, ſo he prayeth for euer without end, <hi>It is God that iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 34.</note> 
                  <hi>who ſhall condemne? it is Chriſt which is dead, or rather riſen againe, who is alſo at the right hand of God, and maketh requeſt for vs,</hi> and as we euer
<pb facs="tcp:5879:24"/> ſinne, ſo the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>He</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 7. 25</note> 
                  <hi>euer liueth to make interceſſion for vs.</hi> There he ſtandeth before the Altar in the preſence of his father with a <hi>golden Cenſer:</hi> for his pretious body which hath bin ſo often tryed as golde in the fire of perſecution, is now glorified in the heauens, which before was an earthen veſſell. In which cenſer there wanteth no fire, for he hath caried al his affections &amp; bowels of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with him into heauen, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may we thinke that he ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth leſſe zeale or loue in his breſt towardes mankinde now ſitting in glory, then bleeding in the garde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or dying vpon the croſſe. It was the effect of the theefe his petition, <hi>Lord reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 23. 42.</note> 
                  <hi>me when thou co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meſt into thy kingdom,</hi> now in the midſt of torment I know thou canſt not
<pb facs="tcp:5879:24"/> forget vs, ſince thou art parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of the ſame miſery with vs: but wilt thou reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber me whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all is paſt, and thou come into thy kingdom; when thy body is glorified, &amp; all teares wiped from thine eies, ſhall not thoſe pittifull affections be alſo wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped from thine hart? no verily though he be aſcended aboue the heauens &amp; <hi>ſtand behind the wall,</hi> though the heauens be <note place="margin">Cant. 2. 9.</note> drawne like a Curtin, or ſtand like a brazen wall betweene, that we cannot behold our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued with bodily eies, yet eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now alſo <hi>doth he looke through the grate vpon vs,</hi> with no leſſe pittiful compaſſion then when hee hanged vpon the croſſe: for when that bloudie enemie <hi>Saul</hi> made a breache into his Church, it affected him as much, as if his owne perſon
<pb facs="tcp:5879:25"/> had been aſſaulted afreſh, <hi>Saul, Saul, why doeſt thou perſecute me? I am Ieſus of Nazareth</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Acts. 9. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>whome thou perſecutest.</hi> When the bleſſed martyr <hi>Steuen</hi> ſtood at the barre in great diſtreſſe, then did he beholde our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our <hi>ſtanding</hi> at the right hand of his Father, as Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Act. 7. 55. Reu 8. 3.</note> doeth here ſee him <hi>ſtanding</hi> before the Altar; who is wont to ſit at the right hand of the maieſtie in the higheſt places; but when his Chucrh is trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, then doth hee ſtand vp and make interceſſion for the ſame, ſuch is his ſympathie and compaſſion towards vs.</p>
               <p>Vpon this heauenly fire doth he powre ſweete odours, and offereth them to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, togither with the prayers of Saints. So then here is our comfort, though our Cenſers
<pb facs="tcp:5879:25"/> be vncleane; yet our prayers are offered in his golden Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer before they be preſented vnto God: and though they be in themſelues neuer ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, yet are they ſweetned and perfumed by the ſweete odours of Chriſt: in whome there is more vertue to purifie and reforme them, then is or can be corruption in our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to infect them.</p>
               <p>Therefore (to conclude) ſince we are not able of our ſelues, as of our ſelues, to <note place="margin">2. Cor. 3. 5.</note> thinke a good thought; let vs deſire the holy ſpirit by his ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall inſpirations, to raiſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie deſires in vs: and ſince thoſe deſires when they are at the holyeſt, muſt needes ſmell of the caske; let vs humbly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate our Sauiour Chriſt to take them out of our naughtie
<pb facs="tcp:5879:26"/> veſſels, and offer them in his golden Cenſer, to perfume them with his ſweete odours, to preſent them in his owne name for vs: ſo ſhall they be a ſweete ſauour vnto God the Father, to whome with his beloued Sonne and bleſſed ſpirit (what euer become of vs) be giuen all glorie, powre, and domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ende:</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:5879:26"/>
            <head>A Prayer for this <hi>time of</hi> viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Eternall and euer-liuing God, Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſer of all things in heauen &amp; earth, wee thy poore creatures bound in dutie to giue thee humble thankes for that great benefite of our
<pb facs="tcp:5879:27"/> creation, whereby thou didſt raiſe vs out of the duſt, aboue other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, to bee made con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to thine owne ſelfe: doe acknowledge here before thy deuine and vnſpotted Maieſtie, to our ſhame and confuſion, that by our owne onely default wee haue vtterly depriued our ſelues, not onely of the comfort of that moſt excellent bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite, but of all power to be dulye thankefull for the ſame.</p>
            <p>Wee haue blemiſhed thine honour, defaced thine Image, brought a
<pb facs="tcp:5879:27"/> curſſe vpon our ſelues, and miſerable thraldome vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the reſt of thy good creatures. Wee haue left our ſelues nothing but mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie and wretchedneſſe, ſhame and nakedneſſe; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but mortalitie, ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours of death, fearefull expectation of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and euerlaſting confuſion.</p>
            <p>And albeit there be left vnto vs ſome reliques of vnderſtanding, as the can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle-light of nature for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, by which we are able to diſcerne ſome few things vnder heauen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet when wee conſider how
<pb facs="tcp:5879:28"/> ſome of our brethren, made of the ſame mould, are borne into the worlde naturall fooles, and ſtarke ideods; who by due might challenge as much as the beſt of vs: wee are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by driuen to confeſſe, that this ſmall remnant of thine image is deriued vnto vs, not by any right of inheritance, but onelye by the indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of ſuch a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full creatour, who in the middeſt of thy iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes doeſt remember mercie.</p>
            <p>Yet curſed creatures that wee are, no ſooner
<pb facs="tcp:5879:28"/> doe wee receiue a good guift of nature from thee, but wee arme our ſelues thereby the more to worke miſchiefe: tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſweeteneſſe into poyſon, and imploying all the naturall powers and faculties of ſoule and bodye as inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes and weapons of vnrighteouſneſſe vnto wickedneſſe.</p>
            <p>Inſomuch, as if thou ſhouldeſt not by thy prouident power binde in that bagge of poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and reſtraine the roote of bitterneſſe within vs, but ſhouldeſt ſuffer
<pb facs="tcp:5879:29"/> it to ſproute out into the ſeuerall branches, wee ſhould too too ſoone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wraye what monſters we are.</p>
            <p>Thus are we by nature plunged into the depth of woe, and expoſed vnto all miſerie: ſo that if all the plagues vnder heauen ſhould zeaſe vpon our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and ſend our ſoules headlong into thoſe hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh torments; we doe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fainedly acknowledge, that thou in thy iudgements might thereby reape ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and we our moſt iuſt deſeruings.</p>
            <p>Yet notwithſtanding
<pb facs="tcp:5879:29"/> for all this, we are encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to approach to thy throne of mercie, as to a moſt gracious God, and our louing Father in Ieſus Chriſt (O bleſſed be that ſonne who hath taught vs to call thee Father) in whoſe onely name and mediation we come vnto thee, beſeeching thee vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our vnſeigned repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to be reconciled vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs.</p>
            <p>Wee repent, O Lorde helpe our impenitencie, wee are out of loue with our ſelues, we deteſt our ſelues for offending ſuch a gratious God: we are ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb facs="tcp:5879:30"/> for our ſinnes, and hartilie ſorrie that wee cannot bee more ſor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie: yet accept our ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, O Lorde, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don our infirmities.</p>
            <p>Teach vs more and more by thy holye ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite to make the true vſe and application of the merites of thy ſonne, to our ſoules and conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Let his humanitie en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage vs with confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to come vnto thee in the name of our elder bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Let his holy concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion dayly purifie our ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall corruption where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in wee were conceaued
<pb facs="tcp:5879:30"/> and borne; that it neuer bring forth more of this corrupt and bitter fruite, as it hath done in the courſe of our liues. We haue multiplyed manye actuall tranſgreſſions and foule offences againſt thy diuine maieſtie: but yet thy ſonne did neuer tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe in all his life: he was obedient to euery iote and tittle of thy lawe for our ſakes: looke vppon his righteouſneſſe. We were ſlaues vnto Sathan, but his paſſion hath redeemed vs: bound with the chaine of ſinnes, but his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation before <hi>Pilate</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:5879:31"/> hath abſolued vs: borne to eternall death; but quickned by his death to euerlaſting life: curſed creatures we were, but his croſſe hath bleſſed vs: polluted and vncleane, but his bloud hath waſhed vs.</p>
            <p>Let all the luſts and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections therefore of our olde man be buried with him, that wee may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed in ſpirit by vertue of his reſurrection: and ſo ſhall wee haue the lotte of our heauenly inheritance daylye more and more confirmed vnto vs, by his aſcention: and we ſecured
<pb facs="tcp:5879:31"/> of all bleſſings meete and conuenient for the mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant eſtate of thy king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, by his ſeſſion at the right hand of the Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie.</p>
            <p>Yea theſe woundes of our conſciences which do now ſeeme to bleed afreſh vnder thy heauie hand of viſitation, ſhall be ſuppled and healed vp by the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne vnction of thy gracious ſpirit deſcending vpon thy Church, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilling from the head to euery liuely member of the ſame.</p>
            <p>And ſeeing thou haſt yeelded thus farre vnto vs
<pb facs="tcp:5879:32"/> (moſt gracious Lorde) we hope further that thou wilt not denie vs any tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall bleſſings which may ſtand with thy glorie and our comfort.</p>
            <p>Then let this great death &amp; mortalitie which nowe reigneth bee ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed vp in the death and paſſion of our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour: Let his ſweete In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe make a ſpeedie at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonement for vs: Let it appeaſe thy wrath which is gone out againſt vs, and ſtay this plague that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun amongſt vs.</p>
            <p>O Lorde, we haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued a thouſand plagues
<pb facs="tcp:5879:32"/> wee confeſſe, but wee are ſorrie for it: Holde thy hand therefore (good fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) and we will doe no more ſo.</p>
            <p>Leſſe of thy iudgement (ſweete Ieſus) leſſe of thy iudgment, and more of thy grace, that wee may make the true vſe of thy iudgements: ſo ſhall our happie deliuerance mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter matter of praiſe and thankeſgiuing in thy holy congregation, to the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall glorye of thy bleſſed name, and comforte of thine elect children.</p>
            <p>Theſe thinges, and whatſoeuer our vnperfect
<pb facs="tcp:5879:33"/> prayers are not able to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, which thou in wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome knoweſt to be need<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full for vs and expedient for thy whole Church, we humbly begge at thy hands for Ieſus Chriſt his ſake, thy beloued Sonne and our only Sauiour and redeemer.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:5879:33"/>
            <head>¶ Another direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>by the line of</hi> the Lords Prayer, to <hi>the ſame purpoſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> LORD our GOD moſt <note place="margin">Our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> gracious and mercifull, we giue thee hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thankes, for that thou haſt vouchſafed to giue
<pb facs="tcp:5879:34"/> vs leaue to come ſo neere thy Maieſtie, as in the name of children to call thee Father.</p>
            <p>Wee are aſtoniſhed (O Lorde) at this great mercie, that thou wilt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge vs for thine owne children, who are ſo vnlike the father: vglie and deformed as <hi>Mephi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boſheth;</hi> diſobedient and profligate runagates, who like the Prodigall ſonne haue ſpent our time and waſted all thy good gifts and bleſſings in the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of this wretched worlde: diſloyall, vnna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, rebellious as <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolon,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:5879:34"/> who by our obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacie, and vnkinde actes, by our moſt cruell and wicked attempts againſt ſo tender and louing a Father, haue deſerued a thouſande vntimelye deaths.</p>
            <p>Yet notwithſtanding <hi>Dauid</hi> could bee no more tender in affection and loue towards <hi>Abſolon,</hi> then thou art ouer vs thy vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracious and wicked chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
            <p>Hee deſired to haue dyed for his Sonne: but thou haſte giuen thine onely Sonne, a thouſand times more pretious in
<pb facs="tcp:5879:35"/> thy ſight, then <hi>Abſolon</hi> could be in <hi>Dauids,</hi> to dye for vs. How ſhouldſt thou not then with him giue vs all things? ſince by him thou haſt made vs ſonnes, wee hope that in him thou wilt denie vs nothing.</p>
            <p>And albeit wee doe nowe feele to our great griefe, that we haue gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſlie offended thee, and that thou art highlye diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed with vs; yet wee hope this thy correction, will prooue but the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſment of a Fatherlie af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection: for thou art not <note place="margin">Which art in Heauen.</note> like earthly fathers, who
<pb facs="tcp:5879:35"/> change their affections as themſelues are corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but <hi>thou art in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,</hi> the ſame for euer, and thy yeares doe not faile.</p>
            <p>Thou art the Father of lights, in whome there is no mutabilitie nor ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe of change. Thoſe whome thou loueſt, thou loueſt vnto the end: but alas wee haue changed, wee haue ſtarted aſide like a broken Bowe: we haue gone awaye, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is the light of thy countenance turned from vs. Yea our ſinnes haue made ſuch a thicke cloud
<pb facs="tcp:5879:36"/> that it cannot ſhine vpon vs. And becauſe we haue ſo abuſed thy patience, and preſumed too farre vpon thy Fatherlye kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, therefore now it pleaſeth thee to teach vs, that <hi>thou art in Heauen,</hi> and wee vpon the earth: that thou canſt humble vs at thy pleaſure, and make vs by thy iudgementes euen to tremble before thy footſtoole.</p>
            <p>Teache vs therefore (Gracious GOD) ſo to comforte our ſelues by thy mercies, that wee ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer preſume to offend: and ſo to humble our
<pb facs="tcp:5879:36"/> ſelues in the conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our ſinnes and thy iudgements, that wee ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer diſpaire of thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour: Aſſuring our ſelues that thou art both able and willing as well to raiſe vs vp as to beate vs downe: <hi>For thou art in Heauen,</hi> and canſt do what thou wilt.</p>
            <p>And as the heauen is aboue the earth, ſo is thy glorye to bee preferred <note place="margin">Hallowed be thy name.</note> before the happineſſe of all the creatures in the world.</p>
            <p>Gloryfie thy name (O Heauenlye Father) and teache vs euer-more to
<pb facs="tcp:5879:37"/> conſecrate the firſt fruites of our deſires, and pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>titions, to the hallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſanctifying of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Sanctifie vs by thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ſpirite, that wee may ſanctifie it, whoe haue blemiſhed the ſame by our former wicked liues, whereby wee haue giuen thee iuſt cauſe to glorifie thy ſelfe in our confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: but thou doeſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes affect more glorye out of mercie then iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Be mercifull therefore O Lorde in theſe our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries: deliuer vs from the
<pb facs="tcp:5879:37"/> power of death and the contagion of this noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome peſtilence, and teach vs by thy fatherly affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hereafter with more ſinceritie to hallow, and ſanctifie thy bleſſed name. So ſhall a Crowne of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry be ſet vpon our heades, by the <hi>comming of thy king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Thy kingdom come.</note> A worthy guift: worthy for ſuch a father to giue, though wee moſt vnworthy to receiue it: yet it is thy fatherly plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to giue vs a kingdom, to make vs heires and fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low heires with thy ſonne Ieſus, who carrieth the ſcepter in heauen for vs,
<pb facs="tcp:5879:38"/> and raigneth within vs by his holye ſpirite, till he haue ſubdued all his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies vnder him: which that wee may enioy giue vs grace <hi>to doe thy will:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Thy will be done.</note> for it is not euery one that ſaith Lorde, Lorde; but hee that doeth thy will which ſhall enter into thy kingdome.</p>
            <p>Giue vs grace to doe, and patience to ſuffer thy good will and pleaſure, whatſoeuer it be: ſo ſhall <hi>thy will<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> bee done</hi> euerye waye, by vs, and with vs, to the hallowing of thy name, and enlarging of thy kingdome: and that
<pb facs="tcp:5879:38"/> not with murmuring and grudging, but moſt wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly by vs <hi>In earth as it</hi> 
               <note place="margin">In earth as it is heauen.</note> 
               <hi>is in Heauen,</hi> where Angels and Cherubins doe thy will, flying with all cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſſe and alacrytie, where the Sunne is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die eyther to ſtaye his courſe, or to goe backe againe, euen againſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, at thy commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Make vs then, as the ſheepe of thy hands, both to obeye thy voyce wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linglie, and patientlie to ſuffer thy good pleaſure. Then wilt thou bee our Shepheard and defender,
<pb facs="tcp:5879:39"/> and wee ſhall wante no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thing: then ſhall the peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of nature be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table vnto thee <hi>Our daylye</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Giue vs this day, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>bread,</hi> and all neceſſaries for this preſent life ſhall by thy fatherly proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence be miniſtred vnto vs.</p>
            <p>Giue vnto vs wee pray <note place="margin">Bread.</note> thee, in this time of weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and viſitation, the ſtaffe of bread to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then our bodies, and ſtrength of bodie to digeſt our bread.</p>
            <p>We pray for no dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties (good father) but for bread, deſiring neither rit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches nor pouertie; but a
<pb facs="tcp:5879:39"/> ſufficient meane of <hi>our</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Our bread.</note> 
               <hi>owne</hi> that we may not bee chargeable but rather helpefull vnto others.</p>
            <p>Enlarge our bowels of compaſſion towardes our poore brethren which pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh for wante of ſuccour, that our bread in theſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed times may bee made common as our praiers are common. And ſo long as it pleaſeth thee to extende our mortall liues, ſo long make a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plye of <hi>daylie</hi> electuaries for the preſeruation or the <note place="margin">D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> bread.</note> ſame.</p>
            <p>Let our ordinary pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and <hi>daylie</hi> porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:5879:40"/> bee miniſtred in due ſeaſon vnto vs. Teach vs ſobrietie in the dayly vſe of thy creatures, that wee glutte not our ſelues at once, and wante another time.</p>
            <p>Teach vs wiſdome, that wee may knowe how to abound and how to want, how to humble our ſelues in faſting, and how to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce in proſperitie; that wee neuer forget the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction of <hi>Ioſeph.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We beg not for yeares, or moneths, or manye dayes: onely giue vs <hi>this</hi> 
               <note place="margin">This day.</note> 
               <hi>daye</hi> our dayly bred: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe wee meane to come
<pb facs="tcp:5879:40"/> againe to morrowe, and be daylye beggers at thy gate of mercie.</p>
            <p>Wee knowe it is thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly goodneſſe, that wee ſhould aske a little and often, to the end we may growe familier with thee in prayer: and that thou maiſt open the windowes of heauen wider, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleniſh our bodies with all plentiouſneſſe; we be ſeech thee to ſhutte the mouth of hell likewiſe, which gapeth ſo wide vpon vs. Remoue from vs all theſe euils which depriue vs of thy forenamed bleſſings: but eſpecially our ſinnes,
<pb facs="tcp:5879:41"/> 
               <hi>Forgiue vs our treſpaſſes,</hi> for <note place="margin">Forgiue vs our treſpaſſes.</note> they haue made this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration betweene thee and vs: they haue diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honoured thy name, ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhed thy Kingdome, diſanulled thy will, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pryued vs of manye bleſſinges, and brought thy heauye iudgementes vpon vs.</p>
            <p>Forgiue, and forget good father: wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe they bee our debtes, wee are not able to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere one of a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, wee haue forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted our bond, nothing remayneth to vs but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall impriſonment in
<pb facs="tcp:5879:41"/> vtter darkeneſſe.</p>
            <p>Onelye let it ſuffice that the hande writing againſt vs for this debt, is nailed to the Croſſe by thy ſonne and our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our.</p>
            <p>Releaſe vs therefore of <note place="margin">As we forgiue them that treſpaſſe againſt vs</note> all that is paſt, and mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifie our hartes with thy grace, that wee may meite the ſame meaſure to our brethren as thou haſt done vnto vs. But of all loue leaue vs not thus neither, for Sathan will bee ſure to aſſault vs afreſh with his <hi>temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Leade vs not into tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> to ſpie where wee bee weakeſt that hee may
<pb facs="tcp:5879:42"/> reenter with greater force, and more malice then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p>Then ſhall the end of vs bee worſe then the beginning: Then ſhall Plague and Peſtilence, Warre and Famine, bee but the beginnings of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe.</p>
            <p>Therefore ſecond vs by the aſſiſtance of thy gracious ſpirite, that wee bee neuer ouer-taken with any dangerous relapſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our former vile tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions: but freed, and <hi>deliuered from all euill,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deliuer vs from euill.</note> both ſpirituall and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, that wee may
<pb facs="tcp:5879:42"/> ſerue thee not as ſeruants, but with that freedome of ſpirite which becom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meth thy adopted chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
            <p>But eſpeciallie deliuer vs from that great euill the Deuill, the arche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enimie to thee and thy Church, in whoſe king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and power all euill is included.</p>
            <p>Theſe thinges graunt vnto vs, (O gracious Sauiour) not for ought in vs, but for thy owne <note place="margin">For thine is thy kingdom, &amp;c.</note> names ſake, for hereby thy kingdome ſhall be enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, thy power manifeſted
<pb facs="tcp:5879:43"/> and thy name gloryfied, wherevnto with hart and voyce we moſt wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linglie ſubſcribe ſaying, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:5879:43"/>
            <head>A Prayer to be <hi>ſaid by thoſe whoſe</hi> houſes be infected.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>RATI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous God, whoe in Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus art the Father of mercies, and God of all
<pb facs="tcp:5879:44"/> conſolation: Wee thy poore creatures, nowe humbled vnder thy migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie hand in ſoule and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, entirelye deſire thy Fatherlye goodneſſe, to pardon and forgiue vs all our ſinnes, which haue ſo poyſoned and infected our ſoules, as the conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion thereof hath euen zeaſed vpon the outward man.</p>
            <p>Cleanſe and waſhe vs wee beſeech thee in the blood of the Lambe, that the ſting of death neuer haue power ouer vs vnto a ſecond death. Confirme and ſtrengthen vs in the
<pb facs="tcp:5879:44"/> faith of thy ſonne againſt all the temptations of Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>than, comfort vs in thy promiſes againſt the force of death: perfect our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance in the due exa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mination of our ſelues, and aſſure our conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, by the teſtimonie of thy ſpirite, that whether wee liue or dye wee ſhall bee thine. As it is thy propertie alwayes to haue mercie, ſo haue thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies euer-more then ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned moſte gloriouſlye, when wee ſtand in grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt need of them, which thing of all others hath been the greateſt comfort
<pb facs="tcp:5879:45"/> to thy children in their greateſt diſtreſſe, that though they haue walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed through the vallyes of the ſhadowe of death, yet they haue feared no euill, becauſe thou haſt euer beene with them, yea thy rodde and thy ſtaffe hath then beene moſte readye for to comforte them.</p>
            <p>Deare Father, now is the time, yea the time is come wherein wee long for mercie: death is at the doore, in the houſe, it compaſſeth vs round: wee walke in the vallie of the ſhaddowe of death.
<pb facs="tcp:5879:45"/> Giue vs grace that wee feare no euill: for death is but a ſhaddowe, the ſtrength and ſubſtance of it is taken awaye in the death of thy Sonne, the ſting is loſt in the wounds of our bleſſed Sauiour, it may ſcare vs a little, but cannot hurt vs.</p>
            <p>And though wee bee compaſſed in, that wee come not foorth, though wee bee ſhutte vp from our neighbours, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of all earthly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte: yet bee thou pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with vs by thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſpirite, and wee ſhall not be deſolate: for thou
<pb facs="tcp:5879:46"/> Lorde alone ſhall make vs dwell in ſafetie.</p>
            <p>Open therefore our eyes of faith, that we may diſcerne a greater force of ſpirituall ſouldiers with vs then againſt vs. Let thine Angels guarde vs in this miſerable life from all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, vntill they carrie our ſoules into thy fatherlye boſome.</p>
            <p>Heauenly Father, who haſt made vs preſerue vs: for thou art a faithfull Creatour, who deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt not in deſtroying the worke of thine owne hands.</p>
            <p>Sweete IESVS thou
<pb facs="tcp:5879:46"/> ſonne of the Father, who haſt redeemed vs, keepe vs: for thou haſt deerely bought vs.</p>
            <p>Holye ſpirite of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte, that haſt taken ſuch paines with vs, dwell in vs vnto the end, and in the end.</p>
            <p>Bleſſed Trinitie, Father, Sonne, and Holy-ghoſt, who haue created, redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and preſerued vs thus farre, leaue vs not at the laſte gaſpe, but heare our cryes, receiue our prayers, eyther to the reſtoring of vs in this life to the glorifying of thy name amongſt men:
<pb facs="tcp:5879:47"/> or, if it bee thy pleaſure, to the receiuing of vs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy euerlaſting habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>Theſe things and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo-euer elſe may ſtande with thy good pleaſure and our comforte, wee begge them at thy hands (O eternall Deitie) not onelye in the name and mediation of IESVS CHRIST, becauſe wee are vnworthye to offer anye thing in our owne names: but alſo becauſe our prayers are vnperfect and earthlie, wee come in his very wordes and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript forme of Prayer,
<pb facs="tcp:5879:47"/> who is beſt acquainted with the ſtile of heauen, and with whoſe name and prayer, and wordes thou muſt needes be well pleaſed.</p>
            <closer>Our Father which art in heauen: Hallowed be thy name, &amp;c.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
